<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="actions_templates" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Actions and templates</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Without using Atomik, one way of doing things would have been to create a file
			per page. The page logic (i.e. connecting to a database, handling form data...) would
			have been at the top of the file followed by the HTML. 
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>A file in the old way</title>
			<programlisting>
				<![CDATA[
					<?php
						if (count($_POST)) {
							echo 'Form data received!';
						}
					?>
					<form>
						<input type="text" name="data" />
						<input type="submit" value="send" />
					</form>
				]]>
			</programlisting>
		</example>
		<para>
			This is BAD!! The application logic and the presentation layer should always be separated.
		</para>
		<para>
			Now let's imagine that rather than directly doing both part in the same file we split it.
			We would have three file: one with the logic, one with the HTML and on that include both.
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Splitting into multiple files</title>
			<programlisting>
				<![CDATA[
					/* ------------- page_logic.php ---------------
					
					<?php
						if (count($_POST)) {
							echo 'Form data received!';
						}
					
					/* ------------- page_html.php ---------------
					
					<form>
						<input type="text" name="data" />
						<input type="submit" value="send" />
					</form>
					
					/* ------------- page.php ---------------
					
					<?php
						include 'page_logic.php';
						include 'page_html.php';
				]]>
			</programlisting>
		</example>
		<para>
			Now replace the third file (the one with the includes) with Atomik and you'll have the concept
			behind Atomik. The logic script is named an action and the html one a template.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Actions</title>
		<para>
			Actions are stored in the <filename>/app/actions</filename> directory. Both the action and the 
			template filename must have the same name.
		</para>
		<para>
			The content of the action file is free. It can be anything you want. So you just do your
			logic as you used to.
		</para>
		<note>
			Be aware that action run in their own scope and not in the global scope as you
			might think.
		</note>
		<para>
			Variables declare in the action are forwarded to the template. If you want to keep some
			variables private (i.e. which will only be available in your action) prefixed them
			with an underscore.
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Private variables in actions</title>
			<programlisting>
				<![CDATA[
					<?php
						$myPublicVariable = 'value';
						$_myPrivateVariable = 'secret';
				]]>
			</programlisting>
		</example>
		<note>
			You shouldn't use <function>echo</function> or write any HTML code inside an action.
			As said before, the goal of an action is to separate the logic from the presentation. Thus
			mix-in both in the action file would be a non-sense!
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Templates</title>
		<para>
			Templates are stored in the <filename>/app/templates</filename> directory.
		</para>
		<para>
			The content of the template file is, as the action file, free. It should mostly be text or 
			HTML (or any presentation content, such as XML).
		</para>
		<para>
			PHP can be used to print variables from the action or to provide presentation logic like
			loops.
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Example template</title>
			<programlisting>
				<![CDATA[
					<html>
						<head>
							<title>Example</title>
						</head>
						<body>
							<?php echo $myPublicVariable; ?>
						</body>
					</html>
				]]>
			</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Calling actions or templates programmatically</title>
		<para>
			When executing a request, the action and/or the template associated to it are
			automatically called. You can however call other actions or render other
			templates using Atomik's API.
		</para>
		<para>
			The most useful use of this it to render partial templates, small part of presentation
			code that is reusable.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Executing actions</title>
			<para>
				To execute an action use the <methodname>Atomik::execute()</methodname> method. It takes
				as first argument the action name.
			</para>
			<para>
				By default, if a template with the same name is found, it is rendered and the return value
				of the <methodname>execute()</methodname> method is the template output.
			</para>
			<para>
				If no template is found or <code>false</code> is used as second argument, the return value
				is an array containing all <quote>public</quote> variables from the action.
			</para>
			<example>
				<title>Calling an action programmatically</title>
				<programlisting>
					<![CDATA[
						$templateOutput = Atomik::execute('myAction');
						$variables = Atomik::execute('myAction', false);
					]]>
				</programlisting>
			</example>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Rendering templates</title>
			<para>
				To render a template use the <methodname>Atomik::render()</methodname> method.
			</para>
			<para>
				It takes as first argument the template name and optionally as second argument
				an array of key/value pairs representing variables.
			</para>
			<para>
				The method returns the template output.
			</para>
			<example>
				<title>Rendering a template programmatically</title>
				<programlisting>
					<![CDATA[
						$templateOutput = Atomik::render('myTemplate');
						$templateOutput = Atomik::render('myTemplate', array('var' => 'value'));
					]]>
				</programlisting>
			</example>
		</section>
		<para>
			For more information on both methods, see the API reference.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
